<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ignoramus justices being an answer to the order of sessions at Hick's-Hall, bearing the date the 13th of January, 1681, wherein it plainly appears the said order is against law : also a short account of all the acts that relate to Protestant dissenters at this day in force against them ... : and also an account of such acts as are in force against popish recusants ... : and hereunto is also added a brief account of the penalties and forfeitures of those acts ... / by Drawde Kekatihw.</title>
            <author>Whitaker, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65679</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1702</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30190</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11258724</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11258724</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47183</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65679)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47183)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1452:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ignoramus justices being an answer to the order of sessions at Hick's-Hall, bearing the date the 13th of January, 1681, wherein it plainly appears the said order is against law : also a short account of all the acts that relate to Protestant dissenters at this day in force against them ... : and also an account of such acts as are in force against popish recusants ... : and hereunto is also added a brief account of the penalties and forfeitures of those acts ... / by Drawde Kekatihw.</title>
                  <author>Whitaker, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ab. Green,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47183:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47183:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Ignoramus Iuſtices:</hi> Being an ANSWER to the ORDER of SESSIONS at <hi>Hicks's-Hall,</hi> Bearing Date the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> 1681. Wherein it plainly appears, the ſaid ORDER is againſt Law.</p>
            <p>ALSO A ſhort Account of all the ACTS that relate to Proteſtant Diſſenters At this day in force againſt them, which will appear only two, <hi>viz.</hi> The Act made in the 22 year of this King, intituled, <hi>An Act againſt Conventicles.</hi> The other, called, <hi>The</hi> Oxford <hi>Act, or Five mile Act,</hi> made in the 17 of this King.</p>
            <p>AND ALSO An Account of ſuch Acts as are in force againſt <hi>Popiſh Recuſants,</hi> which are now ſo induſtriouſly endeavoured by thoſe Juſtices as well as others, to be turned againſt the <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters;</hi> And wherein it will plainly appear, there is no ground for ſuch Proceedings.</p>
            <p>And hereunto is alſo added A brief Account of the Penalties and Forfeitures of thoſe Acts, and ſome Directions to the Officers that may be threatned or perſuaded to Act by ſuch Unwarrantable Orders from ſuch <hi>Ignoramus Juſtices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Drawde Kekatihw.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Ab. Green.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:47183:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47183:2"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Ignoramus Iuſtices:</hi> Being an ANSWER to the ORDER of SESSIONS at <hi>Hicks's-Hall,</hi> Bearing Date the 13th of <hi>January,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE Author hath no other Deſign in publiſhing theſe Sheets, than what the worthy Juſtices of <hi>Middleſex</hi> pretend by their ORDER, <hi>The good Peace and Welfare of the Countrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here, becauſe the ORDER comes out in Form of a Proclamation, with the King's Arms in the Front, I ſhall treat it with all the Modeſty and Civil Terms imaginable; yet I muſt needs reflect in the Latine, as the Form: For the Title, though it be not above three lines, yet one of them is lame Latin; it ſaith in the ſecond line, (viz.) <hi>Poſt feſtum Epiphanie fcilicet tertio decimo die</hi> Januarii, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now with Mr. <hi>Adderly's</hi> good leave, that drew up the learned ORDER, it might better have been <hi>decimo tertio die</hi> Januarii. And that in an ORDER publiſhed in this Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Form, Mr. <hi>Adderly</hi> ſhould take no more care, but ſtumble at the very Threſhold, is very ſtrange, ſomething like his being heretofore miſtaken in a Cauſe of his own againſt the Earl of <hi>Shaftesbury,</hi> wherein he as ignorantly confeſſes in open Court, that he had bought the place of <hi>Clerk of the Peace</hi> ſome time ago for a great Sum of Money; which the Court obſerving,<note place="margin">Michael <hi>Term,</hi> Car.</note> told him, That inſtead of helping himſelf by the abuſive Action he had brought againſt the Lord, he had now abuſed himſelf, by that confeſſion of buying his Place, for now by Law he could not hold it, having forfeited it, as by the Act made in the 5th and 6th of <hi>Edw.</hi> VI. cap. 16.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:47183:3"/>
            <p>But to let Mr. <hi>Adderly</hi> alone, and come to the order in Subſtance, having done with the title, and therefore not to medle with what has been ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in a late paper, <hi>Intituled, An Anſwer to the Juſtices of</hi> Middleſex <hi>Order,</hi> as to their inſinuating to the people their tender care of his Majeſties Gratious Order, which the Juſtices made as a preamble to theirs; nor to mention what was there hinted in that paper of the Juſtices Acting contrary to the Vote of Parliament, and the many other abſurdities in their former Order, of which that paper ſufficiently as well as juſtly condemns. But my deſign is to lay theſe Gentlemen more open, as their Merits deſerve, from the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond excellent Order.</p>
            <p>The firſt Order I ſuppoſe was put forth as a Tryal of Skill, or more properly an experiment was intended to be made by them, whether or no the Conſtables and other Officers would willingly be made Informers by Intreaty, Force, or Compulſion at their Arbitrary will and pleaſure of theſe Worthy Juſtices, under a pretence of Law, and it may be 'twas to try how fit the Officers backs were for a Pack-Sadle, or their Feet for wooden Shoes, againſt the time that ſome men fear ſhould be tried upon Engliſh Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; if the Juſtices had this reach with them, it was moſt excellent and rare, tho it did not abſolutely ſatisfie their full deſires, as indeed by this Order now they ſeem to own in part (that is) that full Obedience was not paid to the former Order of the 22 of <hi>December</hi> laſt by ſome, which appears by their own ſhewing in this ſecond Order (<hi>viz.</hi>) To which Order obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience was given by many of the ſaid Officers, but others appearing in Court did contemn their Authority, for which contempt ſeveral fines were by the Court ſet upon them, &amp;c. So thus it appears by their own ſhewing a kind of party <hi>perpale</hi> ſome did obey, and ſome did not; ſome did pin their Faith upon the Juſtices's Sleeves, where no Law commanded them ſo to do, as the <hi>By-gott</hi> Church men do upon the <hi>Popes</hi> and Prieſt Sleeves, but others did not, therefore they were fined for their Obſtinacy, and for not learning more Manners and Obedience to the Juſtices Order, I had almoſt ſaid <hi>Bulls.</hi> Well then ſince it is ſo, that ſome did obey and ſome did not, in charity to thoſe that did not I muſt take leave to conſider the Point; for theſe Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Officers for their Comfort I may aſſure them, that neither the Juſtices at the Seſſions when that Order of <hi>December</hi> was made, nor the Juſtices at the quarter Seſſions when this Order of the Thirteenth of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary,</hi> was made, had any power by the Conventicle Act of the 22 of this <hi>King,</hi> to medle or make therewith as a Court, either by ſuch Orders as theſe, or any other wayes as a Court at the Seſſions, and that appears thus in the 22d. of this <hi>King.</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi>)</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:47183:3"/>
            <q rend="italic">
               <p>It ſhall and may be Lawfull to and for any one or more Juſtices of the Peace of the County, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Wherein the Offence aforeſaid ſhall be committed. And he and they are hereby required, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Upon Proof to him or them reſpectively made of ſuch Offence, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Confeſſion of the party, or Oath of two Witneſſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">22 ſect</note> To make a Record of every ſuch Offence under his or their hands and Selas reſpectively, which Record ſo made, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Shall to all intents and purpoſes be in Law taken and adjudged to be a full and perfect Conviction of every ſuch Offender, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Now what agreement the Reader can find in this Clauſe with this Order, is worthy the Conſideration, for this Clauſe ſaith expreſly, <hi>One or more Juſtices of the Peace ſhall act upon the Oath of two Witneſſes, and ſo make a Record and thereupon Act.</hi> And the Order ſaith, That <hi>for not executing their Order grounded upon the Act, as the Juſtices would have the World</hi> believe, <hi>they have fined thoſe Officers for not obeying the ſame;</hi> though there is not one word in the Order, that makes mention of a Conviction of any particular perſon upon Oath, or a Record made before them of the Offenders, which ought to have been done before any Conſtable or other Officer can or ought to obey them upon this Clauſe.</p>
            <p>In the next place, it appears not in this Clauſe, nor no other in the whole Act, that the Order is rightly grounded; for the general or quarter Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have no power in the leaſt to make any Orders upon the Act, nor indeed to act upon this Law, unleſs by way of Appeal of the Defendant, and at his inſtance againſt the Juſtices actings upon the Convicting of any one by the Witneſſes, this appears <hi>moſt plain in the ſixth Section,</hi> viz. <hi>Provided, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <q rend="italic">
               <p>That in all Caſes of this Act, where the Penalty or Summe char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon any Offender exceeding the Summe of ten ſhillings, and ſuch Offender ſhall find himſelf agrieved, it ſhall and maybe lawful,<note place="margin">See ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> &amp;c. To appeal in Writing, &amp;c. To the judgment of the Juſtices of the Peace in the next quarter Seſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:47183:4"/>
            <p>Now here is all that is mentioned in the Act that Relates to the Seſſions, and whether this will any way ſupport the Order or is directly oppoſite to the Order, let the Reader be judge; and certainly if thoſe Juſtices, as they pretend, have fined any perſon for not obeying their former Order by which the Officers were commanded to turn Informers, and to give in their Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation at the next Seſſions, I doubt not but theſe Perſons ſo fined or Impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, will Traverſe thoſe Fines, and take a legal Courſe with thoſe Juſtices that Committed them, becauſe they would not Act upon ſuch unlawful Warrants and Orders which have no Coherence with the Act. And this I muſt obſerve by the way, that all Penal Statutes, eſpecially ſuch an one as this which convicts a man without Juries, muſt be exactly obſerved to the very Letter, and not to the extravagant ſence of Petty Juſtices, which will pull buſineſs into their Courts of Seſſions that they have not the leaſt warrant or colour for and againſt the expreſs Law they pretend to Act by.</p>
            <p>In the next place the Order goes on, viz. <q rend="italic">And whereas this Court hath thought fit to make another Order to the ſame end and purpoſe, and hath given the ſaid Officers time to make their return upon it the firſt day of the next quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Seſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which mild way of proceedings this Court hopes will prevail up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the mimdes of all Sober Perſons, both Preachers and Hearers, in Conventicles to avoid all occaſions which may induce this Court to inflict ſuch Penalties upon them as by Law are appointed to ſuch Offenders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Now be pleaſed to marke the Coherence of this wiſe Order, not only in that there is no ſemblance with the Act, but how it is jumbled together, as if the Conſtables and Officers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were not the perſons ſpoke to for to do the Juſtices Work, but as if their Order ſhould hit the Conventicles through thoſe under Officers, or as if by threatning the ſending of Thunder-bolts amongſt the Conſtables, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of a Court, ſhould hit every man elſe whom they imagine are Conventiclers, let us conſider a little this wiſe Order in this part: for as it ſaith, <q rend="italic">Since they did not do their Duty before, but was obſtinate ſome of them, now they ſhall have longer time,</q> and why longer time, becauſe the Conventiclers being ſuppoſed Sober men may thereby take warning by the Court: Now I would know of thoſe Juſtices, if in the whole Act any men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made of a Court to have any ſuch power, in the next place what have the Conventiclers, if Sober men, to do between the Conſtables, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the Juſtices certainly, if the Conventiclers be ſober or not ſober, they have no concern in the Juſtices and the Conſtables quarrels, at leaſt till by name they are convicted, but how can this ſtand with reaſon that the Juſtices pretend, <q rend="italic">viz. Thai Seditious Conventiclers are diſturbers of the Peare,</q> as by the Order and the Act ſeemes to confirm; and yet at the ſame time the Order calls ſuch Sober men, certainly it was the firſt time that ever any Court
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47183:4"/>called Diſturbers of the Peace ſober Men; but if it ſhall be admitted by the Juſtices, that all Conventiclers are ſober Men, now will that agree with the ſame Order, in the next Part, that calls Breakers of the Peace, and a danger even to the Monarchy it ſelf, and keep up the Diviſions that are amongſt us, certainly no ſober Man can do ſuch things, yet all ſuch Men as do meet in a Seditious, Riotous manner, under colour of Religion, with Force and Arms, do break the Peace, and therefore cannot be called ſober Men.</p>
            <p>But I ſuppoſe the Juſtices have this reach with them, that ſince they have made the firſt learned Order, and no notice taken of it, they are reſolved by this Order to ſhew themſelves moderate Men, such as would do ſomething to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue their places, though it be but to make a noiſe in the County. Therefore I ſhall ſay no more to them as to this part of the Order only; but that if ſober Men do meet to worſhip and ſerve God by ſinging of Pſalms, Praying and Preaching, not under a pretence of ſerving of God, but in reality, then both as a Court, or as ſingle Juſtices, nor yet their Officers, whom they ſo hotly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, can meddle or touch ſuch by this Act, or any other Law. And if they have any Information of any other Meetings, they will do well to extend their power for the ſuppreſſing them ſo far, as the Act of the 22 of this King, or the Common Law allows them: And if they venture farther, let them look to it, there is the ſame Law againſt them, as againſt other Men.</p>
            <p>There is another paſſage cannot be omitted to be taken notice of in that Order, which is, viz. <q rend="italic">Which in all probability will deſtroy both Church and State. This is the Opinion of this Court, and of the Juſtices with whom His Majeſty hath been pleaſed to intruſt the Peace of this County, which makes them not ſit ſtill and ſuffer a few obſtinate Perſons, rather by noiſe, than Number, to diſturb the peace of it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Well done, careful Juſtices of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> what a Comfort muſt it needs be to His Majeſty, that He hath been bleſſed with ſuch good Juſtices, careful, diligent, foreſeeing men; But now I would fain know, if theſe good Juſtices of <hi>Middleſex</hi> are only intruſted with the Peace of the County, or if the High Sheriff of <hi>Middleſex</hi> and the Lieutenants, Deputy Lieutenants, High Constables, Petty Constables, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Are not as well truſted with the care of keeping the Peace as well as the Juſtices, though indeed they are not Juſtices upon the Bench, yet ſure as great a Truſt, if not greater, is repoſed in theſe Officers as well as theſe worthy Juſtices, and therefore in Civility ſure it had not been amiſs if theſe Juſtices had given a little Honour to others as well as all to themſelves; but let them a lone at preſent, and let us come to the matter more fully, than to diſpute their Stewardſhip.</p>
            <p>They tell us Conventicles in all probability will deſtroy both Church and State, from whence we may perceive that they are not only intruſted with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47183:5"/>the Peace of the Kingdom but more than probable are endowed from above with the Spirit of Prognoſtication too, or at leaſt a very great foreſight far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our late Parliaments; for they could not ſee one half ſo far, though I dare not mention that too much, for fear of the ſnarling Popiſh Curs (the word Parliament or Houſe of Commons) being but once named, unleſs to Ridicule it is enough in our days to be Termed a <hi>Whigg</hi> or a <hi>Phanatick</hi> at leaſt; But may not this queſtion be put without offence to any, that is, Why how come this jealouſie now all of a ſudden, or <hi>Alamode de France,</hi> more now than it hath been theſe 19 or 20 years laſt paſt, can the Juſtices inſtance in one Riot or Diſturbance of the Government, either in Church or State, all this while they have been Tollerated both before and ſince the Declaration for Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, by the Conventiclers; and pray how comes it, The Juſtices at the Court of <hi>Hicks's-Hall</hi> did not foreſee it ſooner, but it may be the late Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Star hath now enlightned their eyes which before were darkened; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever if it be ſo, the Conventiclers have cauſe enough for ought I ſee, to be very angry at the Blazing-Star for enlightning their eyes now againſt them, when a Parliament is ſo far off from helping them; however the Juſtices are very modeſt, for they only give it as their opinion, but this their opinion they tell us makes them not ſit ſtill, indeed if they ſhould ſit ſtill, it might be a thing of dangerous Conſequence, even no leſs than the hazard of the Church and the whole Kingdom, if their Prognoſtications be true: but I do not wonder if they cannot ſit ſtill themſelves when all is in danger, for by and in another part of the Order, you will finde they cannot ſo much as let the Biſhop ſit ſtill neither, as we ſhall ſee hereafter. But let us proceed further as to this part of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and you will finde that all the great cauſe of theſe Juſtices fear ariſes but from a very ſmall thing, next to nothing, for they tell you, <q rend="italic">They cannot ſit ſtill becauſe of a few obſtinate Perſons rather by noiſe, than number, do diſturb the Peace.</q> Now if it betrue that it be but a few, it may be anſwered then, what need all this noiſe of the Juſtices, ſure a few of theſe Conventiclers may eaſily be dealt with without all this ado, as if the King and Kingdom were at Stake; And if it be true, that they make more a noiſe than number, methinks the Juſtices ſhould by the courſe at the Common Law, ſilence their noiſes, and not be beholding to the Act, that gives the Court of Seſſions no power at all to act by; and how is it poſſible that ſuch a few making a noiſe, can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbe the Peace of the whole Kingdom, and bring ruine upon it, as the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der affirms.</p>
            <p>But to make a full mends for all their Jealouſies and Fears, in the next place they tell us, viz. <q rend="italic">They do eſteem in a Duty incumbent upon them, to uſe all lawful Experiments which may beget <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion amongſt His Majeſties Subjects, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now here they have hit the Point, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niting of Subjects;</hi> that is, proſecute
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47183:5"/>the Conſtables and Under-Officers, becauſe they will not turn Informers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Law, and Preſent and Convict the ſober Proteſtant Diſſenters that go to Meetings in a peaceable manner; this is the Juſtices way, or rather the Courts Order, to have Union among His Majeſties Subjects; but I ſuppoſe the Order means Popiſh Subjects, for no Man of Senſe can ſay this is to unite the Proteſtant Subjects.</p>
            <p>Well, but what follows in the next place, that the Juſtices at the Court may be both amiable and admirable, and a Pattern and good Example to all Juſtices of other Counties, as well as their own, as they were in the late Addreſſes and Preſentment, they have gone a great deal further than the common ſort of Loyal Subjects, for being jealous, I ſuppoſe, of their own power, by the Law of the Land, you will find in the next place, to ſhew their great Zeal for the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of His Majeſties Subjects, they have not ſtuck to ſet the Biſhops Courts to work, to Excommunicate theſe few noiſe Hereticks, for in the next Part of the Order, it follows, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="italic">It is therefore by this Court deſired, That the Lord Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> will pleaſe by ſuch methods, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to direct, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as in wiſdom he ſhall, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> within his Juriſdiction, to uſe his utmost endeavors that all ſuch Perſons may be Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, who ſhall commit Crimes deſerving Eccleſiaſtical Cenſure, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>So that by this it ſeems, the very Juſtices themſelves then believed they had not Law enough to puniſh thoſe Conventiclers, or elſe by the Order it ſhews them moſt cruel and inhumane. What, muſt the Conventiclers be puniſhed both ways at once, both Common Law and Canon Law? Loſe their Eſtates by the Act, and their Souls by the Spiritual Court too? This is ſure more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane, than <hi>France</hi> to their Diſſenters that are fled over here; they do but take away their Eſtates and Children, but not their Souls that they eſcape over here with. Well, ſince it is ſo, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Diſſenters muſt be thus dealt with, it is time to look about them, and conſider the Biſhop's power as well as the Juſtices.</p>
            <p>But before we ſay any thing of that, we muſt conſider the Order a little more as to this Head, and that is, how the Clergy came to be ſtirred up by the Lay-men, to proſecute the People about their Souls health. It is true, we often find in the Popiſh time, that the Clergy and great Biſhops have often in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited and ſtirred up the Magiſtrates and Lay-men to burn the Hereticks, and keep them in Priſon up the Writs, <hi>De Heretico Comburendo,</hi> and <hi>De Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municato Capienda,</hi> and to ſupplicate the Courts for theſe Writs and Proceſs againſt the Excommunicated; but never was it heard before, that the common Lawyers or Juſtices ſued to the Biſhops, for their Fellow-Subjects and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to be ſent to Hell: If this be Law, and to keep the Peace of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> then pray let us complain no more of the <hi>French</hi> King uſing his Proteſtants hardly; for ſure to any unbyaſs'd Man, this looks ten times worſe than the <hi>French</hi> Perſecution, being little leſs than to incite the Biſhops to diſturb the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47183:6"/>Publick Peace, and to uſe an Arbitrary Power, like their own deſigns. But now, after this malicious incitation of this Order, to ſhew the reaſon of their inſtructing or inciting the Biſhop, to ſend the Souls of Hereticks to Hell, they make this further improvement of it, in caſe they can get the thing done; and they have this great deſign in it, that all ſuch as are ſo Excommunicated, do not only loſe their Souls, being given up to Satan, but alſo they loſe all their earthly Freedom and Enjoyments, as <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> as the Juſtices by this learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Order conceive, and therefore as a further miſchief or kindneſs to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, by way of Caution, they lay down the Evils that attend this dreadful thing of Excommunication, which is, viz. <q rend="italic">And to the end that all His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Subjects may know what Inconveniences do attend that Puniſhment, this Court thinks fit to publiſh, That no Excommunicated Perſon may be a Witneſs, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned upon Juries, or to Sue for any Debts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Really if this be ſo, what a miſerable condition ſhall His Majeſties Subjects be in that go to Conventicles, if they muſt both loſe their Eſtates, and then their Souls, and be neither Jury-men, Witneſſes, nor ſue for Debts, What ſhall they do then, if this be true? But, as good Luck is, the Juſtices have as little Law here to back them in theſe Aſſertions, as they have Law for their Orders; For, with their good leave, there is no Law to bar any Man that is Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated from ſuing for his Debt: Nor is there any Law that diſables a Man from being a Jury-man that is Excommunicated, unleſs he be taken upon the Writ, and then indeed he cannot be a Jury-man, until he be at Liberty: No more can a Priſoner, which is a Priſoner for Debt, be a Jury-man, until he have his Liberty to come out; and with, or without the leave of the Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, a Perſon Excommunicated may be as well a Witneſs as any other Perſon; nay, a Perſon Outlawed may be a Witneſs: So that it appears this Order was made without Book, as well as without Law.</p>
            <p>There is another Paſſage in the Order which I cannot paſs over, and that is more Gall yet; but before I take notice of that, I muſt take leave to tell theſe worthy Juſtices of the Court that made this learned Order, that they have implored help of thoſe that are as Lame and Inſufficient in Spiritual Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction as to Excommunication, as they the Juſtices are in their Temporal Puniſhments; for that in truth, the Biſhops in their Spirtual Courts, or Courts Chriſtian, have no power by Law to Excommunicate any perſon, let the Crime be what it will, unleſs by the King's Authority, and with His Commiſſion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Broad Seal.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee Stat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Eliz.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ook cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ops <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ourts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſſolved.</note> This will appear moſt plainly, by the ſeveral Acts of Parliament that relate to Spiritual Juriſdiction, a ſhort Account thereof, with the Arguments, were publiſhed ſome time ſince, in a Book, Intituled, <hi>The Biſhops Court diſſolved,</hi> Printed in 1680. And ſee Mr. <hi>Hickeringill's</hi> Books, one of their own Tribe: But not to build upon thoſe Books, look into the ſeveral Statutes ſince the 21 of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. and you will find their whole co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercive Power taken from them. And if you compare the Statutes of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47183:6"/>1 <hi>Eliz. Edw.</hi> 6. and ſo all along, to 16 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. and the 13 of this King; you will find not only their whole Power taken from them, as to their adminiſtring of Oaths, but that all they have done and acted ſince the laſt Act of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnity, is againſt Law, and the Biſhops and Judges of Spiritual Courts throughout <hi>England,</hi> are all guilty of a <hi>Praemunire,</hi> if the King of <hi>England</hi> ſhall queſtion them for it; and they are at this day liable to be Indicted or Sued by Action, at the Suit of the Party grieved for Damages, by all ſuch as they have at any time Excommunicated in their Courts, ſince the laſt Act of Grace: But to leave the further diſcourſe of this matter till another oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity.</p>
            <p>And ſince the Juſtices have deſired my Lord Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> to Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate at his Pleaſure, or as his Wiſdom ſhall think fit, it may not be amiſs for the Biſhop to take notice of their unkind treating of him in their very next deſire; for, as if they diſtruſted his underſtanding in the ways and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of Excommunication, they go on and lay down Rules for him to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that is, viz. <q rend="italic">That the Lord Biſhop will direct, that ſuch Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may be publiſhed in the Pariſh-Churches where the Excommunicated live.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now what is this, but to tell the Biſhop, they doubt he doth not underſtand his Trade ſo well as they, which ſure is a very great piece of Incivility to their Ghoſtly Fathers; for the good Father well knows, that no man can be fully Excommunicated, but it muſt be read in the Pariſh-Church where the Excommunicated live. But I doubt not but the Biſhop will be pleaſed to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give this their Sin of Ignorance in the Eccleſiaſtical Laws, when they appear ſo ignorant in their own Trade of the Common or Statute Laws, as to make ſuch Orders as theſe. But leaſt we draw the anger of the next Seſſions upon us, we will mind but one thing more in their Order, ſo reſembling the King's Proclamation, and that is ſo excellent a thing, that it far ſurmounts all the reſt; for in the next place they tell you, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="italic">And for the further promoting of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of all His Majeſties Proteſtant Subjects, <hi>(Ay, there it is)</hi> it is Ordered by this Court, That the Juſtices of the Peace in their ſeveral Diviſions, take care that the Statutes <hi>1 Eliz.</hi> and <hi>3 Jacobi,</hi> be put in due Execution, for levying One ſhilling upon thoſe perſons that do not come to their Pariſh, or ſome other Church or Chapel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is to be applied for the Relief of the Poor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is hoped by this Court, that this pious and charitable Work will not be neglected, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>For Anſwer to this laſt Part, we muſt conſider both the Care, Charity and Good-will of the Juſtices here towards the Proteſtants, for till now you hear not a word of Proteſtant Subjects; and if they had miſſed it here, I cannot well tell how this Order could have eſcaped the ſentence of a Popiſh Order; but this clears the Point. However, for theſe Juſtices Order to adviſe one another to put the Laws of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> and 3 <hi>Jacobi</hi> in Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution againſt Conventiclers, as if thoſe Acts related to the Conventicle
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47183:7"/>Act, is ſomething ſtrange; but I ſuppoſe we ſhall find they did this by gueſs too, as all the reſt of the Order, hoping, it may be, they never read thoſe Acts, or at leaſt it being ſo long ſince they have read them, that they have totally forgot them; for if they had remembred the ſubſtance of thoſe 2 Acts, they could not have been ſo miſtaken, as to bring them in play to puniſh Conventicles, thoſe Laws being only made againſt the Papiſt, and none elſe, as will appear by and by. But firſt it will not be amiſs to take notice how the Juſtices in this Order interweeve one Act with another, and not only ſo, but endeavor all the Puniſhments both that the Church and the State can inflict upon the Conventiclers, double and treble Puniſhments, and all is, becauſe but a few Subjects, as they call them, do differ from the Church of <hi>England</hi> in ſome Ceremonies, not in Doctrine at all. But that which I mean is this, the Juſtices are not ſatisfied with a ſingle Puniſhment for one and the ſame Fact, but that they ſhall be proſecuted by them firſt, and then Excommunicated, and then pay 12<hi>d.</hi> a week, all at a time. To ſhew their Error, and better inform their Judgments, if they pleaſe to conſider all Laws made for or concerning any ſuch Church-matters, do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide, That if the Parties offending be once puniſhed by the Civil Magiſtrate, or once puniſhed by the Church-Cenſures, the Party ſo puniſhed by either of them, ſhall plead to the other Court that he was Sued or Proſecuted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in another Court for the ſame thing, which Plea ſhall abate the Action or Libel. To prove this, you will find it Enacted in the very Statute the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mentions, 1 <hi>Eliz. Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Sect.</hi> 24. And ſince we are now upon this Act as a farther Confirmation of what has been before touched on, That the Juſtices, as a Court of Seſſions, have no Power to act upon the Conventicle Act, there being in that Act no power given them in that Act aforeſaid, ſo to do as in other Acts there is, to confirm it further in this Act of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> there is a Clauſe on purpoſe: <q rend="italic">That the Juſtices of Oyer and Termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and Gaol-Delivery, and Seſſions of the Peace, ſhall have power in their Seſſions to hear and determine all Offences committed againſt that Act.</q> And if thoſe Juſtices of <hi>Middleſex</hi> can find ſuch a Clauſe in the Conventicle-Act, then undoubtedly they are right, and their Orders of Seſſions, and General Warrants of Seſſions good; but unleſs they can produce ſuch a power in that Act, I am ſure their Orders and Warrants are Illegal and Arbitrary: But as to the Union mentioned hereof, the Proteſtants, and the Charity they intend to the Poor, by gathering the Forfeitures of the Act to be given to the Poor; Was it ever known before, that Force and Proſecution of Penal Laws againſt one another, was a way to Union? Doth not Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Reaſon tell us, That <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> are to be dealt with by Lenity, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion, and ſtrong Arguments? Force did never yet work upon <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> but Flattery hath: And doth theſe Juſtices think, That becauſe they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with the Peace of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> they are intruſted with the Souls, Minds
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47183:7"/>and Conſciences of Men? Now if they have that Truſt too, then I confeſs all is well, and an Union will be had by their forcing without doubt, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe not. But I have this reaſon to believe, that an Union cannot be had this way, by proſecuting Men, becauſe I well know, that if their Commiſſions were as large again as they are, yet they cannot force Love and Union; nor they cannot make a Man believe by Force, though they may make a Man for Fear ſay he believes. And as to their Charity and Good-works, as they call it, of proſecuting the Conventiclers for not coming to Church, it cannot ſink into any reaſonable Mans brains, that the Poor will be much the better for that Charity which comes by Blood; that is, the forcing of Mens Conſciences, methinks it looks like ſtrange Charity.</p>
            <p>But as to the two Acts mentioned, that of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> and 3 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> and all other Acts that are made againſt <hi>Popiſh Recuſants,</hi> which are now by theſe Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and divers others, deſigned to ſerve a turn againſt <hi>Diſſenting Proteſtants</hi> from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in defiance of the thing called Parliaments; for they have declared the Laws before-mentioned, and all others made againſt <hi>Popiſh Recuſants,</hi> ought not to be put in Execution againſt the <hi>Proteſtant Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters;</hi> and to be farther aſſured of that, ſee the Vote, viz. <q rend="italic">Sabbati ſexto die <hi>Novembris 1680.</hi> Reſolved, <hi>Nemine Contradicente,</hi> That it is the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of this Houſe, That the Acts of Parliament made in the Reigns of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> againſt Popiſh Recuſants, ought not to be extended againſt Proteſtant Diſſenters.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But we muſt have a care too, that the naming of Parliament Votes, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the Houſe of Commons, do not make worſe for the Proteſtant Cauſe; for in Truth, the Houſe of Commons have been ſo run down, that for any one now to but ſpeak of them, or their good Votes and Intentions, is to be ſtig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matized for a down-right Diſloyal Perſon. Well then, ſince thoſe Laws are threatned to be turned againſt Proteſtant Diſſenters from the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> which Church was made by an Act of Parliament, called the Act of Uniformity in the 13th, and 14th of this King, it may not be amiſs to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them what they are, and how many they are,<note place="margin">See St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> 13 and Car. 2.</note> and the occaſion of making them againſt the Papiſt, that ſo the Proteſtants may make the better Defence againſt them, if thoſe Juſtices, or any other, ſhall make uſe of them as this Order ſeems to drive at We will begin with the firſt, which is that mentioned in the Order, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> cap. 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This Act was made imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after the Queens coming to the Crown, when ſhe found nothing but Papiſts and Proteſtants in general; for the word Puritan in thoſe days was not known, the light was not then ſo clear, but ſhe being a good Proteſtant, and reſolved to ſupport that Religion with her wiſe Council, caſt about how to do it, that the indifferent and moderate ſort of Papiſts might not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſted and frightned from a cloſing with the Proteſtant Religion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore on mature deliberation, it was concluded to go on gently as to the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47183:8"/>and not throw off all the Superſtitious Ceremonies at once, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore having a Pattern of Proteſtant Diſcipline made in King <hi>Edwards</hi> time, ſhe follows thoſe Steps as near as may be in the beginning, grafting upon King <hi>Ed.</hi> 6 Stock, or rather Foundation, which he by his wiſe and honeſt Councel layd, and therefore the firſt Act ſhe paſſed, was to take off the Juriſdiction of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> and all coercive Power whatſoever from Eccleſiaſtical Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and all was annext to the Imperial Crown of <hi>England,</hi> ſo the Act 1 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1. The Title of that Act is, viz. <q rend="italic">An Act to reſtore to the Crown the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Juriſdiction over the Eſtate Eccleſiaſtical and Spiritual, and aboliſhing all Forreign Powers Repugnant to the ſame.</q> And in this Act power is given to the Queen to grant Commiſſions under the Broad Seal of <hi>England,</hi> to ſuch Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Laymen as ſhe ſhould appoint to hold Eccleſiaſtical Courts, and none might do it without upon pain of a Premunire, ſee more of this Sect 15, 16, 17, 18. and by this Act was repealed, all Laws made in the time of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> for ſetling the Popes Authority in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Act was that mentioned in the Order which is called, <q rend="italic">viz. An Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity and Common Prayer and Service in the Church and Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sacraments.</q> Now this Common Prayer Book was compoſed and taken out of the Maſs uſed before <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. Time, and the way that was then taken to bring the Papiſts over to conform to it, was to tell them, as in truth it was, but the Maſs turned into <hi>Engliſh</hi> for their better underſtanding, and till the People were a little uſed to the Proteſtant Religion, it was not thought rational to leave off all the Ceremonies at once, but by degrees, ſee the wiſe Courſes of thoſe times. Now to prove that this Act was only intended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Papiſts, is moſt plain, becauſe the whole Act runs for the beating down of Popiſh Fopperies and Superſtitions of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and then again, it is impoſſible it could be intended againſt any ſort of Proteſtants, for at that time a day there was but two ſorts of People in <hi>England, viz.</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants and Papiſts, now for the penalty of this Act, it is very various, but as to the coming to Church it is 12<hi>d.</hi> a Week, and this to be levied by the Church-Wardens and Over-ſeers of the Poor, but I confeſs Church-War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens <hi>&amp;c.</hi> muſt have a Warrant before they can diſtrein, and that the Seſſions have power to do upon Conviction, ſee ſect 14, and 15. But other offences Committed againſt the Act, muſt be tryed by Peers, ſee Sect 21. So that upon the whole matter, if the Juſtices ſhall Execute this Act upon the Proteſtant Diſſenters from the now Eſtabliſhed Church of <hi>England,</hi> yet the labour is more than the profit, and therefore can do no great hurt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The next Law in Force againſt Popiſh Recuſants, is the</hi> 23 Eliz. cap. 1. <hi>Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, An Act to retain the Queens Majeſties Subjects, in their due obedience;</hi> which begins thus, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q rend="italic margDblQuotes">Where ſince the Statutes made in the 13 year of the Reign of the Queen our Sovereign Lady, Intituled, An Act againſt the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in, and putting in Execution of Bulls, Writings and Inſtruments, and other
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47183:8"/>ſuperſtitious things from the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp;c.</q> And in the 5th <hi>Section</hi> of the ſaid Act, it goes on, after divers Commands, againſt Popiſh Recuſants too, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q rend="italic">Be it alſo Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that every one above the Age of Sixteen Years, which ſhall not repair to ſome Church, Chapel, or uſual place of Common-Prayer, but forbear the ſame, contrary to the tenor of a Statute made in the Firſt year of Her Majeſties Reign, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And being thereof law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Convicted, ſhall forfeit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for every month, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which he or ſhe ſhall forbare, Twenty Pounds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And beſides the ſaid Forfeitures, <q rend="italic margDblQuotes">Every perſon ſo forbearing by the ſpace of Twelve months, as aforeſaid, ſhall for his or her obstinacy, after Certificate thereof, in Writing, made unto the Commiſſioners, commonly called the Kings-Bench, by the Ordinary of the Dioceſs, Juſtices of Aſſize, Gaol-delivery, or Juſtices of Peace of the County where the Offender ſhall dwell, be bound with two ſufficient Sureties in the Sum of 200 <hi>l.</hi> at leaſt, to the good Behavior, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> So that the whole drift and deſign of theſe two Acts, appears moſt clear to be againſt Papiſts, and Popiſh Superſtitions, for every Clauſe of the Act plainly ſpeaks the ſame, and to put this Act in Execution againſt the Proteſtants would be moſt abſurd. <q rend="italic margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>Sect. 9.</hi> The Juſtices at the Quarter-Seſſions ſhall have power to inquire into the Offences againſt this Act, except Treaſon. And in caſe a perſon were Indicted upon this Act, yet if he would conform in open Court, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that ſhould diſcharge him of all but Treaſon mentioned in the Act, ſo that the conforming were before Judgment given, <hi>Sect. 10.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The next Statute is of 29 <hi>Eliz.</hi> cap. 6. Intituled,<note place="margin">29 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <q rend="italic margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>An Act for the more ſpeedy and due Execution of certain Branches of the Statute made in the 23 year of the Queens Majeſties Reign,</hi> Intituled, <hi>An Act to retain the Queens Majeſties Subjects in their due Obedience.</hi>
               </q> This Statute is a further Expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the two former, and only makes the Penalties greater for <hi>Popiſh Recuſants</hi> Convicted in not frequenting Divine Service once a month. And whereas the former Statute of the 23, was to be only 20 <hi>l.</hi> a month, and bound to the good Behavior after Conviction, this gives power to the Queen and her Heirs, to take 20 <hi>l.</hi> per month for every month after ſuch Conviction, till they ſhall Conform; and if default be made of payment of the 20 <hi>l. per menſem,</hi> then the Queen may ſeize all their Goods, and two parts of the Real and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Eſtate. See the Act, <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>And in the next Paragraph of this Statute, Power is given, That after the Indictment found by the Grand Jury, that Proclamation ſhall be made at the Aſſizes, Seſſions, or Gaol-delivery, for the Perſon to appear; and if he do not appear the next Aſſizes, Seſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he ſhall ſtand abſolutely Convicted. See <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. more at large.</p>
            <p>The next Statute againſt <hi>Popiſh Recuſants,</hi> is 1 <hi>Jac. cap.</hi> 4.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Jacob cap.</hi> 4.</note> which confirms all the former Statutes made againſt <hi>Popiſh Recuſants</hi> in the Queens time, with ſome ſmall additions touching their being diſcharged, though Convicted, upon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47183:9"/>their Conformity to hear Divine Service, as by thoſe former Acts of Hers di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects; and that it plainly appears to mean and intend none but <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Prieſts,</hi> and other <hi>Popiſh Recuſants,</hi> appears manifeſtly, not only in the Title, but in the firſt <hi>Section</hi> of the Act it ſelf, and ſo throughout; the Title is, viz. <q rend="italic">An Account for the due Execution of the Statutes againſt Jeſuits, Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Prieſts, Recuſants,</q> and begins tus, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="italic margSglQuotes">For the better and more due Execution of the Statutes heretofore made as well againſt Jeſuites, Seminary Prieſts, as alſo againſt all manner of Recuſants, Be it Ordained and Enacted by this preſent Parliament, That all and every the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes heretofore made in the Reign of the late Queen of famous Memory <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> as well againſt Jeſuits, Seminary Prieſts, and other Prieſts, Deacons, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and Eccleſiastical perſons whatſoever made, ordained, or profeſſed, or to be made, ordained or profeſſed by any Authority or Juriſdiction derived, challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged or pretended from the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp;c. together with all thoſe made in the ſaid Queens time againſt any manner of Recuſants, ſhall be put in due and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Execution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> So that by this Act, and all the Clauſes in it, can mean nor intend nothing but what the former did, which was againſt <hi>Popiſh Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Act againſt <hi>Popiſh Recuſants,</hi> is 3 <hi>Jacob. cap.</hi> 4. <hi>viz.</hi> Intituled, <q rend="italic">An Act for the better diſcovering and repreſſing Popiſh Recuſants,</q> it begins thus: <q rend="italic margSglQuotes">Foraſmuch as it is found by daily Experience, that many of His Majeſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects that adhere in their hearts to the Popiſh Religion, by the Infection drawn from thence, and by the wicked and deviliſh Counſels of Jeſuits, Seminary Prieſts, and other like perſons, dangerous to the Government of the Church and State, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as evidently appears by that more than barbarous and horrible attempt to have Blown up, with Gun-powder, the King, Queen, Prince, Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, in the Houſes of Parliament aſſembled, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This ſhews plainly the Act was deſigned againſt the <hi>Papiſts</hi> only, not only by the Title, and the words of the Act rehearſed, but that the reaſon of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this, as you will ſee, was, becauſe of the <hi>Powder-Plot;</hi> and the purport of this Act all along, is only to reinforce all the reſt of the Acts againſt <hi>Popiſh Recuſants,</hi> in not coming to Church, and to diſcover them by the Teſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Sacrament once a year, as an additional Tryal of the reality of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> Conforming: For that it appears in the next <hi>Section</hi> of the Act, That ſome of them did come to Church, and heard Divine Service, to ſave the Penalties in the former Acts, and yet continued <hi>Papiſts</hi> in their hearts: Therefore by this Act they were all to take the Sacrament once a year. See <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. which Enacts, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q rend="italic margSglQuotes">And if any Recuſant of conformed, ſhall refuſe to take the ſaid Sacrament of the Lords Supper accordingly, he or ſhe ſhall for ſuch not refuſing, loſe and forfeit for the firſt year 20 <hi>l.</hi> and for the ſecond year, for ſuch not receiving 40 <hi>l.</hi> and for every year after, for ſuch not receiving, 60 <hi>l.</hi> until he or ſhe ſhall have received the ſaid Sacrament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:47183:9"/>
            <p>And by the fourth Section of this Act, the Church-Wardens and Conſtables, are to Preſent the Monthly Abſence from Church of all, and all manner of Popiſh Recuſants, within their Town, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which by the way, it is to be obſerved from this Act, that no man can be Proſecuted or Preſented upon this Act, or any other, it intends, which are all the former rehearſed, unleſs they be Popiſh Recuſants, for ſo are the expreſs words of the Act; and, without doubt, ſhould any buſie Officer whatſoever Preſent or Proſecute any Perſon other than a Popiſh Recuſant, the Perſon ſo Preſented may join Iſſue that he is no ſuch Perſon as theſe Acts intend, being not a Papiſt: Now theſe Acts alſo give the Juſtices, at their Seſſions, Power to inquire into the Offences committed againſt the Acts; but in the Juſtices Order they have quite forgot the Popiſh Recuſants, where they have a Power to do and meddle with that wherein they have no Power, and therefore ought to make that good Confeſſion in the Book of Common-Prayer, viz. <hi>We have left undone thoſe things which we ought to have done, and have done thoſe things which we ought not to have done; and there is no truth in us.</hi> Theſe are all the Acts that are now in Force againſt Popiſh Recuſants, for not coming to Pariſh Churches, and taking the Sacrament as the Act directs; and becauſe it may as well appear what is or hath been made againſt the Puritan Sectaries and Conventicle, I ſhall here briefly ſet them down in order, and to begin with the firſt, and that is the Statute of 33 <hi>Eliz.</hi> cap. 1. Intituled, <hi>An Act to retain the Queens Majeſties Subjects in their due Obedience.</hi>
               <note place="margin">35 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And the Reader will find that this is the firſt Law that ever was made againſt Sectaries and Seditious Conventicles, and this Act is indeed, beyond all diſpute, only made againſt them, and the Popiſh Recuſants are excepted out of it, as will appear by the Act; And becauſe the Reader may the better judg the true difference between this Act and thoſe made againſt Popiſh Recuſants, as to the very expreſs Terms: I have hereinſerted, <hi>verbatim,</hi> the firſt Paragraph of the Act. The Act begins thus, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margSglQuotes">For the preventing and avoiding of ſuch great inconveniences and perils as might happen and grow by the wicked and dangerous practices of Seditious Sectaries and Diſloyal Perſons. Be it Enacted by the Queens moſt Excellent Majeſty, and by the Lords Spiritual and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, and the Commons, in this, preſent Parliament Aſſembled; and by the Authority of the ſame, That if any Perſon or Perſons, above the Age of ſixteen years, which ſhall obſtinately refuſe to repair to ſome Church, Chappel, or uſual place of Common Prayer, to hear Divine Service, eſtabliſhed by Her Majeſties Laws and Statutes in that behalf made, and ſhall forbear to do the ſame by the ſpace of one Month next after, without any lawful cauſe, ſhall at any time after forty days next, after the end of this Seſſion of Parliament, by Printing, Writing, or Expreſs Words, or ſpeak adviſedly, or purpoſely Practice, or go about to make, or perſwade any of Her Majeſties Subjects, or any other within Her Highneſſes Realms or Dominions, to deny, withſtand or impair Her Majeſties Power and Authority, in Caſes Eccleſiaſtical, Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and Annexed to the Imperial Crown of this Realm; or to that end and purpoſe ſhall advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly, or malitiouſly move, or perſwade any other Perſon whatſoever, to forbear, or abſtain from coming to Church to hear Divine Service, or to receive the Communion, according to Her Majeſties Laws and Statutes aforeſaid, or to come to, or be preſent at any unlawful Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, Conventicles or Meetings, under colour or pretence of any Exerciſe of Religion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Her Majeſties Laws and Statutes; or if any Perſon or Perſons which ſhall obſtinately refuſe to repair to ſome Church, by the ſpace of one Month, to hear Divine Services, as it afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, ſhall after the ſaid forty days, either of him, or themſelves, or by the motion, perſwaſion, inticement or allurement of any other, willingly joyn in, or be preſent at any ſuch Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, Conventicles, or Meeting, under colour or pretence of any ſuch Exerciſe of Religion, contrary to the Laws and Statutes of this Realm as is aforeſaid, that then every ſuch Perſon ſo offending, as aforeſaid, and being thereof lawfully Convicted, ſhall be committed to Priſon, and there to remain, without Bail or Mainpriſe, until they ſhall conform and yield themſelves to come to ſome Church, Chappel, or uſual place of Common Prayer and hear Divine Service, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:47183:10"/>
            <p>The next Clauſe is, if they did not Conform within three months after Conviction, they were to be baniſhed, and ſo the Act goes on to Felony at laſt, as you may ſee more at large in the Statute.</p>
            <p>And to ſhew that this Act was wholly intended againſt the <hi>Sectaries</hi> or <hi>Puritans</hi> ſo called in thoſe days, and not againſt the <hi>Popiſh Recuſants,</hi> is clear by what hath been laid down; but that it may not be objected by the Enemies of the <hi>Diſſenting. Proteſtants,</hi> now that all thoſe Acts, as well as this, are to be taken and Conſtrued in Law to be one and the ſame, and that all the aforementioned Acts of <hi>Eliz:</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> are equally to be applyed to all Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from the Eſtabliſhed Church of <hi>England,</hi> I do ſay and affirm, that cannot be; for the <hi>Popiſh Recuſants,</hi> by this Act, are not at all-touched, nor could be Proſecuted upon it: For that in the 12 <hi>Sect.</hi> of this Act,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 12.</note> it is there particularly provided, <q rend="italic">that no Popiſh Recuſant, or Feme-Covert ſhall be compelled or bound to abjure by vertue of this Act.</q> Then it neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows certainly, if the <hi>Popiſh Recuſants</hi> ſhall not be puniſhed by this Act made againſt Sectaries and Seditious Conventicles, That theſe <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Conventiclers</hi> being <hi>Protestant Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> as their Adverſaries will have it, <hi>Proteſtant Recuſants,</hi> for that is it they aim at, to colour the laying the other Acts upon them, That then theſe <hi>Proteſtant Sectaries, Conventiclers,</hi> or <hi>Proteſtant Recuſants</hi> ſhall not be Proſecuted upon thoſe Laws made only againſt <hi>Popiſh Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants,</hi> for if it ſhould be, then you leave the <hi>Proteſtant Recuſants</hi> in a far worſe Condition than the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> the one being provided for, and not the other.</p>
            <p>But that I have ſaid about this Act, comparing it with the other made againſt Popiſh Recuſants, is only to ſhew the unreaſonableneſs of the Juſtices opinion; for the Reader muſt know that I have only mentioned this Act of the 35th. of <hi>Eliz.</hi> but to ſhew the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the one as well as the other; for that this Act of the 35th. <hi>Eliz.</hi> is not in force now, although it is confeſſed it was thought to be in force until the expiration of the Conventicle Act, made in the 16th. Year of this King: but both expired about one Year ſince; for that of <hi>Eliz.</hi> and the Act of the 16th. of this King were in nature one and the ſame. And that of the 16th. of this King, did as ſome think revive the 35th. of <hi>Eliz.</hi> by declaring it in force: but how long? Why it could not be declared for a longer time than it ſelf lived; which dyed about the time aforeſaid, both being but Temporary Acts. And indeed it was a happy turn for this Nation; for had thoſe two Acts been in force, which were ſanguinary Laws, much miſchief might have accrued to the People of this Kingdom: but God be thanked they are gone, and have left none behind them to puniſh the Conventiclers, and the Nonconformiſt Miniſters, who did not conform to the Act of Uniformity made in this Kings Reign: But the Conventicle Act made the twenty ſecond of this King, and the Act com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the Five Mile, or <hi>Oxford</hi> Act; which is all can be raked up againſt the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Proteſtants by Law, as I conceive at this day; which two Acts I ſhall a little conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and firſt for the <hi>Oxford</hi> or Five Mile Act, made in the 17th. of this King <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. Intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2.</note> An Act for reſtraining Nonconformiſts from Inhabiting in Corporations: by this Act all ſuch Perſons as are in Holy Orders, Eccleſiaſtical Perſons as well as others, that did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the Act of Uniformity, made the 14th. of this King, and ſhall take upon them to Teach or Preach, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in any Meeting, Pariſh-Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhall forfeit for every ſuch Offence the ſumm of 40. <hi>l.</hi> to be inquired of in any Court at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> or Oyer and Terminer; Great Seſſions of <hi>Wales,</hi> or Juſtices of the ſeveral Quarter-Seſſions of the Peace; the forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, one third to the King, one third to the Poor, and one third to the Informer, and in the ſame Act, <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. and 4. No ſuch Miniſter, Teacher, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhall teach School, or live, inhabit or abode in any Corporation, or within five Miles of the ſame, or where he laſt had a Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, or near any Borrough that ſends any Members to Parliament, upon the Penalty of 40. <hi>l. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But note, that if on a Jury he may paſs or live in any ſuch Corporation, or appear upon Summons or <hi>Sub-pena,</hi> In the 5th, <hi>Section</hi> two Juſtices together in any County, where the Offence is committed, upon Oath to them made of the Offence againſt this Act, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47183:10"/>the Offender to Priſon for ſix Moneths without Bayl, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> unleſs the Party ſo brought before the Juſtices will take the Oath mentioned in the Act, which is, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q rend="italic">I <hi>A. B.</hi> do ſwear that it is not lawful upon any pretence whatſoever, to take Arms againſt the King, and that I do abhor that Trayterous poſition of taking Arms by his Authority againſt his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or againſt thoſe that are commiſſioned by him, in purſuance of ſuch Commiſſions; and that I will not endeavour any alteration of Government, either in Church or State.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the Penalties of this Act, and if a Perſon be ſo convicted before the Juſtices, if he takes this Oath, he ſaves himſelf from their Power, and from the Impriſonment, which is all they can do out of a Court of Seſſions, the two Juſtices having not Power to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vict as to the 40. <hi>l.</hi> Penalty.</p>
            <p>And as for the Act of the twenty ſecond of this King, for ſuppreſſing ſeditious Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, under pretence of Religious Worſhip, where the Conventiclers meet together, under a pretence of Religious Worſhip, and not according to the Liturgy and Practice of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> if any ſuch there be, the Juſtices knowing ſuch by the Oath of two Witneſſes, may make a Record thereof, and the Perſons ſo offending and convicted before them; the Juſtices have power to Iſſue out their Warrants to the under Officers to levy the ſumm of 5. <hi>s.</hi> a piece upon each Hearer, and 20. <hi>l.</hi> upon the Preacher, and 20. <hi>l.</hi> upon the Houſe, and in caſe of Inſufficiency of the Hearers 10. <hi>l.</hi> upon any Perſon preſent at the ſame Meeting, in lieu of ſuch conceived not able to pay, and it muſt appear upon Oath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe Juſtices by two Witneſſes, or confeſſion of the Parties that it is a ſeditious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle met together, for the diſturbance of the Peace, under pretence of Religious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and it muſt alſo be ſworn before any Conviction can be had againſt any man or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that the People that were met together, was not according to the Liturgy and Practiſe of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> which is next to impoſſibility, to do in the Caſe of moſt Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Middleſex,</hi> and whoever acts upon that Act muſt be ſure he goes not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the laſt: but they that ſhall act as the Order of the Juſtices Commands, outruns both the Law, and the Conſtable that muſt anſwer for the ſame at the pleaſure of him or her that is agrieved, and all the Wit in the Juſtices head cannot ſave them, that do act ſuch things as in that Order is contained; for the Law will find them out, though for a time they may ſave themſelves from the Power of a Parliament, whom they ſeem to affront, and ſcorn, by acting contrary to the very ſence of the Nation, declared by their Repreſentatives.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſhall only add ſome ſmall Notes of Directions to the Conſtables and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder-Officers, who may eaſily be led into a Snare by ſuch Orders and General Warrants, and when they are in, will find it hard to get out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And firſt I affirm, That no Conſtable ought to execute any Order at all, as an Order of Seſſions, or a General Warrant from the Seſſions, in proſecuting this Conventicle-Act, for the Law has plainly preſcribed another Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and they muſt exactly follow it, and not meddle with any other form or manner than as the Law directs; and the Conſtables are not to be afraid of the Juſtices, for they are as well puniſhable, if they act contrary to Law, as the Conſtables and Under-Officers are, either by Indictment, or Action of the Party grieved.</p>
               <p>And as for their General Warrants, printed and dated the 21 of <hi>January,</hi> I conceive them to be as Arbitrary and Illegal, as their Order of Seſſions, for that it commands them to turn Informers upon their Oath to the Juſtices at <hi>Hicks-Hall.</hi> Now under their favor, there is no ſuch thing can be done; for the Seſſions, as is before declared, have no power in the matter; and if they had, they cannot force a man to be an Informer upon his Oath, or otherwiſe, whether they be Conſtables, or other Officers or not.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:47183:11"/>
               <p>In the next place, General Warrants are not legal to apprehend any man upon ſuſpicion of a Fact that may, or is like to be committed, and that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer that acts by ſuch General Warrant, if he ſhall apprehend any Perſon thereon, and it prove that the Perſon ſo apprehended be innocent of the Crimes charged upon him, the Conſtables, or other Officers, are accountable for the ſame as falſe Impriſonment, for that General Warrant will not bear the Officer harmleſs.</p>
               <p>In the next place, as to breaking open of Doors, the Conſtable had beſt have a care of that too, for if through a wrong Information he break open any door other than the Act directs, which is only the Meeting-houſe, in caſe of Refuſal to enter, the Conſtable may be undone, notwithſtanding his Warrant.</p>
               <p>Nor will the Act bear any Conſtable or other Officer out, for doing any thing about the <hi>Conventicles,</hi> unleſs he have firſt a Certificate of ſuch a Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from ſome Juſtice of Peace, and then he may go; and if he find any Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious <hi>Conventicles</hi> which tends to the breaking the Peace, he ought to execute his Warrant ſo far as is agreeable to the Act, but to turn Informer, Promoter, or Eaſtee-man, unleſs in caſe of a Riot, or ſuch like, the Conſtable can do no ſuch thing but at his own Peril.</p>
               <p>In the next place, the Warrant commands you the Conſtables to aſſemble the Headboroughs, Churchwardens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to agree together for putting the ſaid Order in execution.</p>
               <p>This you may do if you will, or let it alone, and much better than do it, for this is to make your Office more burdenſom than ever the Law intended it, and is more than all or any Juſtice in <hi>England</hi> can command you; for the thing they command you is not warranted by Law, nor is it practicable, nor indeed ſcarce poſſible, and the very Juſtices themſelves muſt own it, if they conſider this, how impoſſible it is for any number of Men to be forced to agree to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; I would have the Juſtices explain themſelves what they moan by it, that you ſhall force them to agree with you Conſtables. Will they order you to beat them, or impriſon them, or put them in the ſtocks, if they will not agree with you the Conſtables? But if you have ſuch an Order, and are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to obey it, take care you have good Security from the Juſtices to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempniſie you, or elſe it may chance you may ſuffer as a Conſtable, though not as a Juſtice.</p>
               <p>Then in Caſe a Certificate ſhall come to your hands under the Juſtices Hands, of a Meeting in ſuch a place, if you receive it you may go, but if you find none, you are not oblidged to go the ſecond time upon the ſame Certificate, without a freſh notice, unleſs you want work; and if you find any Meeting, and ſee any perſons there which are named in your Warrant, you ought to bring them if you can, but for the Juſtice to impoſe on you the Conſtables the proof againſt ſuch as you find, that the Juſtices cannot do unleſs you will your ſelf, and to force the Officer to ſwear that goes to ſeize, is almoſt impoſſible; for unleſs the Officer were there all the time of the Meeting, he cannot ſwear it a Conventicle; for he muſt ſwear what the people did, and that there was nothing done all the whole time of the Conventicle, but what was contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Liturgy, and practice of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and how any man can do that, it ought to be well conſidered before it be done, leſt he pay for it another day.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:47183:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
